# MUHAMMAD RASHED

2550 N Alafaya Trl, Apt. 10305, Orlando, Florida, 32826 muhammad.rashed@ucf.edu  $\diamond$  +1(210)-910-7104  $\diamond$  Website: https://mrhrashed.github.io/

#### SUMMARY

I am a PhD candidate in Computer Engineering at the University of Central Florida (UCF). My expected graduation date is Spring 2024 and I am on the academic job market for tenure-track assistant professor positions starting Fall 2024. My research interests include EDA for emerging computing paradigms and architectures, computer-aided design, and, artificial intelligence. On these topics, I have published 16 top-tier journals and conference papers. I have a total of 8 publications on the prestigious CSRanking list. My ICCAD paper in 2022 was nominated for the IEEE/ACM William J. McCalla ICCAD Best Paper Award and, my DAC paper in 2022 was recognized as a Publicity Paper at the conference.

#### **EDUCATION**

## University of Central Florida, Orlando

January 2020 - present

PhD in Computer Engineering, Department of ECE

(Expected in Spring 2024)

Thesis: Towards Energy-Efficient In-Memory Computing Systems using Design Automation

Supervisor: Prof. Rickard Ewetz

## University of Texas at San Antonio, San Antonio

August 2018 - December 2019

Graduate Coursework, Department of ECE

### Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

May 2010- September 2015

Bachelor of Science, Department of Electrical and Electronics Engineering

#### AWARDS AND HONORS

• IEEE/ACM William J. McCalla ICCAD Best Paper Award Nomination	2022
• Best Research Video Award at the Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2021
$\bullet$ Acknowledgment of the XORG Paper as a Publicity Paper at $\mathbf{DAC}$	2022
• David T. and Jane M. Donaldson Memorial Graduate Scholarship	2022
$\bullet$ IEEE/ACM DATE PhD Forum Best Doctoral Dissertation Competition Finalist	2023
• IEEE/ACM DAC PhD Forum Best Doctoral Dissertation Competition Finalist	2022
• NSF Travel Grant (2021–2024), DATE Travel Grant (2023), UCF SGA Travel Grant (2023–ACM Travel Grant (2022)	2024),
• The Presentation Fellowship by UCF Graduate Studies	$2021\!-\!2023$
• 3MT Research Finalist at the University of Texas at San Antonio	2019
• Education Board Scholarship for HSC, SSC and JSC result	2005 - 2015

## RESEARCH PAPER PUBLICATIONS

## Major Research Topics:

- Electronic Design Automation (EDA) for Emerging Computing Paradigms
- Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML)
- Computer-aided Design (CAD) for Very Large-Scale Integration (VLSI)
- Computer Architecture

### Peer-Reviewed Publications:

[P20] [ASP-DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "READ-based In-Memory Computing using Sentential Decision Diagrams", 29th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2024. (accepted)

- [P19] [ASP-DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Towards Area-Efficient Path-Based In-Memory Computing using Graph Isomorphisms", 29th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2024. (accepted)
- [P18] [ICCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Automated Synthesis for In-Memory Computing", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P17] [ICCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, H Zheng, and R Ewetz, "Path-based Processing using In-Memory Systolic Arrays for Accelerating Data-Intensive Applications", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P16] [ICCAD'23] S Thijssen, S. Singireddy, <u>M Rashed</u>, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Verification of Flow-Based Computing Systems using Bounded Model Checking", 42nd International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P15] [TCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, F Yao, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "STREAM: Towards READ-based In-Memory Computing for Streaming Based Processing for Data-Intensive Applications", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023
- [P14] [TCAD'23] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "PATH: Evaluation of Boolean Logic using Path-based In-Memory Computing Systems", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023.
- [P13] [ICCD'23] S. Singireddy, <u>M Rashed</u>, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Input-Aware Flow-Based In-Memory Computing", 41st International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD), 2023.
- [P12] [DAC'23] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "UpTime: Towards Flow-based In-Memory Computing with High Fault-Tolerance", in 60th Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2023. [CSRanking]
- [P11] [ASP-DAC'23] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Discovering the In-Memory Kernels of 3D Dot-Product Engines", 28th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2023.
- [P10] [ICCAD'22] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Logic Synthesis for Digital In-Memory Computing", 41st International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2022. (Best paper nomination) [CSRanking]
- [P9] [DAC'22] <u>M Rashed</u>, A Awad, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Towards Resilient Analog In-Memory Deep Learning via Data Layout Re-Organization", 59th Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2022. (Publicity Paper) [CSRanking]
- [P8] [DATE'22] M Rashed, SK Jha, F Yao and R Ewetz, "Hybrid Digital-Digital In-Memory Computing", 25th Design Automation and Test in Europe Conference (DATE), 2022.
- [P7] [ASP-DAC'22] M Rashed, S Thijssen, F Yao, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "STREAM: Towards READ-based In-Memory Computing for Streaming based Data Processing", 27th Asia and South Pacific Design Automation Conference (ASP-DAC), 2022.
- [P6] [ICCAD'21] M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Hybrid Analog-Digital In-Memory Computing", 40th International Conference On Computer Aided Design (ICCAD), 2021. [CSRanking]
- [P5] [MICRO'21] M Chowdhuryy, M Rashed, A Awad, R Ewetz, and F Yao, "LADDER: Architecting Content and Location-aware Writes for Crossbar Resistive Memories", 54th International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), 2021. [CSRanking]

  Prior to PhD:
- [P4] [ICAEE'17] M Rashed, M Zaman, M Islam and M Raihan, "An analysis on the required reinforcement for embedding a nuclear power plant in a generic power system", 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE), 2017.
- [P3] [EICT'17] S Saha, S Ukil and M Rashed, "Numerical investigation on the performance of new ultra-thin CZTS solar cell using SCAPS", 3rd International Conference on Electrical Information and Communication Technology (EICT), 2017.
- [P2] [ICAEE'17] A Dewanjee, N Dey, M Rashed, A Muhury and J Dhar, "High performance cost effective formalin detector using conductivity property", 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE), 2017.

[P1] [ICECE'16] M Nadim, <u>M Rashed</u>, A Muhury and S Mominuzzaman, "Estimation of optimum tilt angle for PV cell: A study in perspective of Bangladesh", 9th International Conference on Electrical and Computer Engineering (ICECE), 2016.

## **Under Review Publications:**

- [U6] [TCAD'23] M Rashed, S Thijssen, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "LOGIC: Logic Synthesis for Digital In-Memory Computing", IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems (TCAD), 2023. (under review).
- [U5] [DAC'24] M Rashed, S Thijssen, D Simon, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Execution Sequence Optimization for Processing In-Memory using Parallel Data Preparation", 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. (under review)
- [U4] [DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Efficient Runtime Management of Crossbars for Path-based In-Memory Computing", 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. (under review)
- [U3] [DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Synthesis of Compact Flow-based Computing Circuits from Boolean Expressions", 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. (under review)
- [U2] [DAC'24] S Thijssen, M Rashed, SK Jha, and R Ewetz, "Efficient Runtime Management of Crossbars for Path-based In-Memory Computing", 61st Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2024. (under review)
- [U1] [ISCAS'24] H. Chugh, <u>M Rashed</u>, F. Yao, and R Ewetz, "Side Channel Attack in ReRAM Crossbar", IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS), 2024. (under review)

## TALKS/POSTER PRESENTATIONS

[T3] [DATE'22] PhD Forum, in 26th Design Automation and Test in Europe Conference (DATE)	2023
[T2] [DAC'22] PhD Forum, in 59th Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2022

[T1] [DAC'21] Young Fellow Program, in 58th Design Automation Conference (DAC)

2021

#### GRANT PROPOSAL WRITING EXPERIENCE

I have assisted my supervisor Prof. Rickard Ewetz with 7 grant proposal submissions on EDA and AI to the National Science Foundation (NSF), Department of Energy (DOE), and, Cyber-Florida. To date, the proposals have been awarded a total grant of \$825,000.

#### Selected Proposals:

- Collaborative Research: FMitF: Track I: Synthesis and Verification of In-Memory Computing Systems using Formal Methods. (Awarded \$750,000).
- Security-Aware In-Memory Neural Networks for Cyber-Physical Systems (Awarded \$75,000).
- An Analysis of Semiconductor Workforce Development using National Science Foundation Support at Hispanic Serving Institutions in the United States.
- Collaborative Research: Elements: Cyberinfrastructure for End-to-End Design, Synthesis, and Validation of In-Memory Computing Systems.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### University of Central Florida

January 2020 - present

Graduate Research Assistant

- Developed a logic synthesis framework for digital in-memory computing. The framework improves the area-latency of multiplication operations by 77% and 20% over the state-of-the-art. [P10], [P17]
- Designed an in-memory systolic array system using path-based in-memory computing. The system is 23X faster than traditional systolic arrays. [P16]
- Developed an efficient 3D dot product engine (DPE) architecture that achieves 2.02X, 2.37X, and 2.45X improvements in area, energy, and latency respectively over 2D DPE. [P11]
- Developed a data layout re-organization framework for analog in-memory deep learning. The framework improves precision in hardware by up to 3.2X. [P9]

- Developed design automation infrastructure for hybrid analog-digital in-memory computing. The hybrid paradigm achieved 2.5X overhead improvement over state-of-the-art paradigms. [P6], [P8]
- Proposed a streaming-based in-memory computing architecture for evaluating Boolean logic. The architecture improves performance over state-of-the-art by up to 20X by eliminating expensive and error-prone WRITE operations. [P13], [P7]
- Delivered an effective and low-cost location and data-aware processor-side architecture for memristor-based memory systems. The framework called LADDER achieves 13.2% performance improvement over state-of-the-art designs. [P5]

## University of Texas at San Antonio

August 2018-December 2019

Graduate Research Assistant

• Developed secure automated vehicular communication protocol between OBU and RSU units.

## Abul Khair Steel Melting Limited

October 2015-June 2018

Technical Management

- Supervised electrical power distribution in the Main Receiving Substation (MRSS).
- Supervised the routine electrical maintenance to circumvent breakdowns. Reduced equipment shut-down by two occurrences per year.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• C++ and Data Structures (UTSA)

Object-oriented programming including data abstraction, inheritance, operator overloading, and polymorphism. Application of OOP to study various data structures including stacks, queues, linked lists, trees, binary trees, and graphs.

- Engineering Analysis and Computation (UCF)
  - Engineering analysis and computation with structured constructs. Subscripted variables, functions, input/output. Applications in embedded systems and examples in numerical methods.
- Guest Lecture/ Course Development: Computer-Aided Design of VLSI (UCF)
  An introduction to computer-aided design (CAD) for very large scale integration (VLSI). The focus is on algorithms and data structures that are used within logic synthesis.

#### MENTORING EXPERIENCE

I have mentored 9 graduate students + 7 undergraduate students + 9 high-school (10-12 grades) students + 1 industry affiliate. (Diversity: 6 female advisees, 2 black students, 2 Hispanic students, 1 first-gen college student, and, 1 student with a learning disability)

#### Selected Advisees

- Sven Thijssen, Ph.D. student @UCF, Achievements: [P20], [P19], [P16], [P14], [P12], [U2-U4]
- Hardik Chugh, MS student @UCF, Achievements: [U1]
- Stacey Alexander, industry affiliate @UTSA
- Suraj Singireddy, Ph.D. student @UTSA, Achievements: [P13]
- Jodh Pannu, PhD student @UTSA

#### PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

• Session Chair, Design Automation Conference (DAC)	2022
• Technical Reviewer, IEEE Internet of Things Journal	2023
$\bullet$ Technical Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Emerging Topics in Computing	2022
$\bullet$ Technical Reviewer, International Symposium on Quality Electronic Design (ISQED)	2024
• Technical Reviewer, International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD)	2021, 2022

• Technical Reviewer, The Great Lakes Symposium on VLSI (GLSVLSI)	2021, 2022
• Technical Reviewer, International Conference on AI Circuits and Systems (AICAS)	2022, 2023

# COMMUNITY SERVICE AND EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITY

$\bullet$ Guiding prospective international students with graduate school application process	2018-present
$\bullet$ Supporting incoming international students at UCF with housing & transportation	2020-present
• Serving in the Bangladesh Student Association (BSA) at UCF	2020-present
• Participating in sporting events of UCF Badminton and Cricket clubs	2021-present
• Served as the Vice President of the Bangladesh Student Association (BSA) at UTSA	2018 - 2019

# **SKILLS**

- Programming Language: C++, Python, MATLAB and Verilog.
- EDA Tools: Design Compiler, ABC, YOSYS, SIS, Vivado Design Suite, CACTI 7, ARM Forge
- Operating Systems and Software: Linux, Windows, Office Software, Latex, AutoCad.

# **TRAINING**

• Responsible Conduct of Research for Engineers- Stage 2 (CITI)	2023
• Authorship, Credit and Collaborative Scholarship (UCF)	2022
• Doing the Right Thing: Know About Research Misconduct (UCF)	2022
$\bullet$ at-risk for University and College Faculty and Stuff (UCF)	2020
• at-risk Friends in College (UCF)	2020
• Employee Code of Conduct & Speak Up Whistleblower Training (UCF)	2020
• Academic Integrity Module (UCF)	2020
• Responsible Conduct of Research for Engineers- Stage 1 (CITI)	2020
• Teaching Assistant Training (UTSA)	2019